<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step name="make-absolute-uris" version-idref="v30" category-idrefs="standard-steps env misc" short-description="Make URIs in the document absolute"
  required="true" publish="true" href-specification="{$BASELINK-STANDARD-STEPS-V30}#c.make-absolute-uris" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xtpxlib.nl/ns/xprocref ../../../xsd/xprocref.xsd"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.xtpxlib.nl/ns/xprocref" keywords="URI absolute">

  <!-- ======================================================================= -->

  <signature>

    <input port="source" content-types="xml html" primary="true" sequence="false">
      <description>
        <para>The document to resolve the URIs in.</para>
      </description>
    </input>

    <output port="result" content-types="xml html" primary="true" sequence="false">
      <description>
        <para>The resulting document.</para>
      </description>
    </output>

    <option name="match" required="true" as="xs:string" subtype="XSLTSelectionPattern">
      <description>
        <para>The XSLT match pattern for the attributes and/or elements that hold the URIs to change.</para>
      </description>
    </option>

    <option name="base-uri" as="xs:anyURI?" required="false">
      <description>
        <para>The base URI to use for making the matched attributes/elements absolute.</para>
        <para>If this option is not specified, the base URI of the matched element/attribute in the source document is used. In most cases this will
          be the location (path on disk) where it originated from.</para>
      </description>
    </option>

  </signature>

  <!-- ======================================================================= -->

  <summary>
    <para>The <step/> step makes element and/or attribute values in the document appearing on the <port>source</port> port absolute by applying a base
      URI.</para>
  </summary>

  <!-- ======================================================================= -->

  <description>

    <para>The <step/> step takes the document appearing on its <port>source</port> port and searches for elements and/or attributes as indicated by
      the <option>match</option> option. The values of these elements/attributes are taken as URIs and, if relative, resolved against a base URI as
      specified in the <option>base-uri</option> option. If there's no <option>base-uri</option> option, the base URI of the element/attribute is
      used.</para>

    <para>Why is this useful? URIs in documents that are edited or received from the web are often relative. They point to other documents, for
      instance images, that are elsewhere on disk or the web, in a location <emphasis>relative</emphasis> to the source document. For instance:
        <code>images/picture.jpg</code>. This allows for flexibility in the location of the documents. However, when processing these URIs and access
      the referenced documents, the code needs to know how to resolve them into absolute ones. It is practical to arrange all this URI resolving in
      advance, and this is what <step/> is for.</para>

    <para>There is an important thing to keep in mind when supplying a value for the <option>base-uri</option> option:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>When its value ends with a slash (<code>/</code>), it points to a <emphasis>location</emphasis>. All URIs are resolved against that
          location. For instance: <code>file:///myapp/images/</code></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>When its value does <emphasis>not</emphasis> end with a slash, it points to a document. All URIs are resolved against the location of
          this document. For instance, for a <option>base-uri</option> value <code>file:///myapp/images/logo.svg</code>, the URIs are resolved against
          the location <code>file:///myapp/images/</code></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The <example-ref idref="basic-usage"/> example shows this difference.</para>

  </description>

  <!-- ======================================================================= -->

  <detail>
    <xi:include href="../../text-fragments/document-properties-preserved.xml"/>
  </detail>

  <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

  <detail>
    <para>The <option>match</option> option must match attributes or elements. If anything else is matched, error <step-error-ref code="XC0023"/> is
      raised.</para>
  </detail>

  <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

  <detail>
    <para>A relative value for the <option>base-uri</option> option is resolved against the base URI of the element on which this option is specified.
      In most cases this will be the static base URI of your pipeline (the path where the XProc source containing the <step/> is stored). This is very
      probably not what you want. </para>
  </detail>

  <detail>
    <para>If no <option>base-uri</option> option is specified and an element/attribute matched has no base URI also, the result is
      implementation-defined and therefore dependent on the XProc processor used.</para>
  </detail>

  <!-- ======================================================================= -->

  <example title="Basic usage" id="basic-usage">

    <para>This example shows what happens to different kinds of URIs when resolved. The <option>base-uri</option> value here points to a
        <emphasis>location</emphasis> (because it ends with a <code>/</code>).</para>

    <xproc-example href="../../examples/make-absolute-uris/make-absolute-uris-01.xpl"/>

    <para>Just to show you the difference, this is what happens when you omit the final <code>/</code> from the <option>base-uri</option> option. Its
      value, <code>file:///X/Y/Z</code>, now points to a <emphasis>document</emphasis> called <code>Z</code>. The URIs are resolved against the
      location of this document.</para>

    <xproc-example href="../../examples/make-absolute-uris/make-absolute-uris-02.xpl" show-source="false"/>

  </example>


  <!-- ======================================================================= -->

  <step-errors>
    <step-error code="XC0023"/>
    <step-error code="XD0064"/>
  </step-errors>

</step>
