<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step name="string-replace" version-idref="v30" category-idrefs="standard-steps" short-description="[EDIT] string-replace short description"
  required="true" publish="false" href-specification="{$BASELINK-STANDARD-STEPS-V30}#c.string-replace"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xtpxlib.nl/ns/xprocref ../../../xsd/xprocref.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xmlns="http://www.xtpxlib.nl/ns/xprocref">
  <signature>
    <input port="source" content-types="xml html" primary="true" sequence="true">
      <description>
        <para>[EDIT] input source</para>
      </description>
    </input>
    <output port="result" content-types="text xml html" primary="true" sequence="true">
      <description>
        <para>[EDIT] output result</para>
      </description>
    </output>
    <option name="match" required="true" as="xs:string" subtype="XSLTSelectionPattern">
      <description>
        <para>[EDIT] option match</para>
      </description>
    </option>
    <option name="replace" required="true" as="xs:string" subtype="XPathExpression">
      <description>
        <para>[EDIT] option replace</para>
      </description>
    </option>
  </signature>
  <summary>
    <para>[EDIT]</para>
    <para>The <tag>p:string-replace</tag> step matches nodes in the document provided on the <port>source</port> port and replaces them with the
      string result of evaluating an XPath expression.</para>
  </summary>
  <description>
    <para>[EDIT]</para>
    <para>The value of the <option>match</option> option must be an XSLTSelectionPattern.</para>
    <para>The value of the <option>replace</option> option must be an XPathExpression.</para>
    <para>The matched nodes are specified with the selection pattern in the <option>match</option> option. For each matching node, the XPath
      expression provided by the <option>replace</option> option is evaluated with the matching node as the XPath context node. The string value of
      the result is used in the output. Nodes that do not match are copied without change.</para>
    <para>If the expression given in the <option>match</option> option matches an <emphasis>attribute</emphasis>, the string value of the
        <option>replace</option> expression is used as the new value of the attribute in the output. If the attribute is named “<tag class="attribute"
        >xml:base</tag>”, the base URI of the element must also be amended accordingly.</para>
    <para>If the document node is matched, the entire document is replaced by the string value of the <option>replace</option> expression. What
      appears on port <port>result</port> is a text document with the text node wrapped in a document node.</para>
    <para>If the expression matches any other kind of node, the entire node (and <emphasis>not</emphasis> just its contents) is replaced by the string
      value of the <option>replace</option> expression.</para>
    <bridgehead>Document properties</bridgehead>
    <para feature="string-replace-preserves-all">If the resulting document contains exactly one text node, the <literal>content-type</literal>
      property is changed to <literal>text/plain</literal> and the <literal>serialization</literal> property is removed, while all other document
      properties are preserved. For other document types, all document properties are preserved.</para>
  </description>
</step>
