<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<about-page xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <!-- ================================================================== -->
  <!--
    Contents of the about page (in DocBook).
  -->
  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <para>The XProcRef site contains reference information about the built-in steps in the <link xlink:href="https://xproc.org/" role="newpage">XProc
      programming language</link>, targeted at language users/programmers.</para>

  <para role="break-after">Please note that the XProcRef step descriptions are <emphasis>non-normative</emphasis>. It&#x2019;s a translation from the
    official, <emphasis>normative</emphasis>, specification into more user-friendly terms. And, yes, things get lost in translation. Sometimes
    formulations are simplified to make their meaning clearer, some details are left-out because they are only important for very rare edge-cases,
    etc. So if you&#x2019;re ever in doubt, remember that the <link xlink:href="https://xproc.org/specifications.html">XProc&#160;specification</link>
    represents the truth!</para>

  <para role="break-after">There is an underlying reason for all this. In 2020 I published a book called &#x201c;XProc 3.0 - Programmer
    Reference&#x201d; (for sale <link xlink:href="https://xmlpress.net/publications/xproc-3-0/" role="newpage">here</link>):</para>

  <para>
    <link xlink:href="https://xmlpress.net/publications/xproc-3-0/" role="newpage">&#160;&#160;<inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/bookcover.png" width="15%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></link>
  </para>

  <para role="break-before">Appendices A and B in the book describe the step library. However, due to time constraints, the step descriptions were
    copied from the formal XProc specification. This leaves much to be desired for users of the language: the specification is aimed at XProc
    processor <emphasis>implementers</emphasis>, not at language <emphasis>users</emphasis>. To correct this, this site contains reference information
    about the XProc steps, written from a more user-oriented perspective. With the increasing popularity of XProc, I hope this fills a need.</para>

  <para role="break-before">Help is always welcome. If you have anything to say, add or comment about something on XProcRef, please <link
      xlink:href="https://github.com/xatapult/xprocref/issues" role="newpage">raise an issue</link>. Or for the more adventurous types: fork the <link
      xlink:href="https://github.com/xatapult/xprocref" role="newpage">XProcRef GitHub repository</link>, make the change yourself, and create a pull
    request. There is a little documentation in the <code>doc/</code> subdirectory.</para>


  <para role="break-before">Erik&#160;Siegel (<link xlink:href="mailto:erik@xatapult.nl">erik@xatapult.nl</link>)</para>
  <para>
    <link xlink:href="https://www.xatapult.com/" role="newpage">Xatapult&#160;Content&#160;Engineering</link>
  </para>

</about-page>
