<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
  <!-- ================================================================== -->
  <!--
    Contents of the Introduction chapter of the PDF version.
  -->
  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <title>Introduction</title>

  <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

  <para>XProc is a programming language for processing XML, JSON, and other documents in pipelines. XProc chains conversions and other steps, allowing
    for potentially complex processing. XProc is especially useful for applications, such as publishing, where content may come from multiple input
    sources, pass through multiple processing steps and result in multiple output streams.</para>

  <para>The basic building blocks of XProc are its <emphasis>steps</emphasis>. A step is something that processes the document(s) flowing through it
    in some way. For instance by changing some attributes, deleting stuff, or using it for accessing resources by HTTP. XProc has many built-in steps
    and you need to know, in detail, what they do to be able to write an XProc program. This book is a reference guide to all defined XProc
    steps.</para>

  <para role="break-before">In 2020 I published a book called “<link xlink:href="https://xmlpress.net/publications/xproc-3-0/">XProc 3.0 - Programmer
      Reference</link>”:</para>

  <para>
    <link xlink:href="https://xmlpress.net/publications/xproc-3-0/" role="newpage">&#160;&#160;<inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/bookcover.png" width="15%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></link>
  </para>

  <para>Appendices A and B in the book describe all the steps. However, due to time constraints, the step descriptions were copied from the formal
    XProc specification. This leaves much to be desired for users of the language: the specification is aimed at XProc processor
      <emphasis>implementers</emphasis>, not at language <emphasis>users</emphasis>. To correct this, I created the website <link
      xlink:href="https://xprocref.org" role="newpage"><code>xprocref.org</code></link>, containing reference information about all the XProc steps,
    written from a more user-oriented perspective.</para>

  <para>Also, since the book was written, the specification was updated to version&#160;3.1. And although the changes are relative minor, details
    count! Both the <link xlink:href="https://xprocref.org" role="newpage"><code>xprocref.org</code></link> website and this book are up-to-date with
    version&#160;3.1.</para>

  <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

  <para role="break-before">Erik&#160;Siegel (<link xlink:href="mailto:erik@xatapult.nl">erik@xatapult.nl</link>)</para>
  <para>
    <link xlink:href="https://www.xatapult.com/" role="newpage">Xatapult&#160;Content&#160;Engineering</link>
  </para>

</chapter>
