<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step name="split-sequence"
      version-idref="v30"
      category-idrefs="standard-steps"
      short-description="[EDIT] split-sequence short description"
      required="true"
      publish="false"
      href-specification="{$BASELINK-STANDARD-STEPS}#c.split-sequence"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xtpxlib.nl/ns/xprocref ../../xsd/xprocref.xsd"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns="http://www.xtpxlib.nl/ns/xprocref">
   <signature>
      <input port="source"
             content-types="any"
             sequence="true"
             primary="true">
         <description>
            <para>[EDIT] input source</para>
         </description>
      </input>
      <output port="matched"
              sequence="true"
              primary="true"
              content-types="any">
         <description>
            <para>[EDIT] output matched</para>
         </description>
      </output>
      <output port="not-matched"
              sequence="true"
              content-types="any"
              primary="false">
         <description>
            <para>[EDIT] output not-matched</para>
         </description>
      </output>
      <option name="initial-only"
              as="xs:boolean"
              select="false()"
              required="false">
         <description>
            <para>[EDIT] option initial-only</para>
         </description>
      </option>
      <option name="test"
              required="true"
              as="xs:string"
              subtype="XPathExpression">
         <description>
            <para>[EDIT] option test</para>
         </description>
      </option>
   </signature>
   <summary>
      <para>[EDIT]</para>
      <para>The <tag>p:split-sequence</tag> step accepts a sequence of documents and divides it into two sequences.</para>
   </summary>
   <description>
      <para>[EDIT]</para>
      <para>The value of the <option>test</option> option must be an XPathExpression.</para>
      <para>The XPath expression in the <option>test</option> option is applied to each document in the input sequence. If the effective boolean value of the expression is true, the document is copied to the <port>matched</port> port; otherwise it is copied to the <port>not-matched</port> port.</para>
      <para>If the <option>initial-only</option> option is true, then when the first document that does not satisfy the test expression is encountered, it <emphasis>and all the documents that follow it</emphasis> are written to the <port>not-matched</port> port. In other words, it only writes the initial series of matched documents (which may be empty) to the <port>matched</port> port. All other documents are written to the <port>not-matched</port> port, irrespective of whether or not they match.</para>
      <para>The XPath context for the <option>test</option> option changes over time. For each document that appears on the <code>source</code> port, the expression is evaluated with that document as the context document. The context position (<code>position()</code>) is the position of that document within the sequence and the context size (<code>last()</code>) is the total number of documents in the sequence. <emphasis role="bold">[ERROR <step-error-ref code="XC0150"/>]</emphasis>
      </para>
      <note xml:id="note-stream">
         <para>In principle, this component cannot stream because it must buffer all of the input sequence in order to find the context size. In practice, if the test expression does not use the <function>last()</function> function, the implementation can stream and ignore the context size.</para>
      </note>
      <para>If the implementation supports passing PSVI annotations between steps, the <tag>p:split-sequence</tag> step must preserve any annotations that appear in the input.</para>
      <bridgehead>Document properties</bridgehead>
      <para feature="split-sequence-preserves-all">All document properties are preserved.</para>
   </description>
   <step-errors>
      <step-error code="XC0150">
         <description>
            <para>It is a dynamic error if evaluating the XPath expression in option <option>test</option> on a context document results in an error.</para>
         </description>
      </step-error>
   </step-errors>
</step>